Chapter 14 For several subsequent days I saw little of Mr. Rochester.
In the mornings he seemed much engaged with business, and in the afternoon
gentleman from Milcott or the neighborhood
called, and sometimes stayed to dine with him.
When his sprain was well enough to admit of horse exercise, he rode out a good
deal, probably to return these visits, as he generally did not come back.
Till late at night.
During this interval, even Adele was seldom sent for to his presence,
and all my acquaintance with him was confined to an occasional wrong contrary
in the hall, on the stairs, or in the gallery, when he would sometimes pass me
haughtily and coldly, just acknowledging my presence by a distant nord or a cool
glance, and sometimes bow and smile with gentleman-like affability.
His changes of mood did not offend me, because I
saw that I had nothing to do with their alternation.
The air been flow depended on causes quite disconnected with me.
One day, he had had company to dinner, and had sent for my portfolio,
in order, doubtless, to exhibit its contents.
The gentleman went away early to attend a public meeting at Milcott.
As Mrs Fairfax informed me, but the night being wet
and inclement, Mr. Rochester did not accompany them.
Soon after they were gone, he rang the bell.
A message came that I and Adele were to go downstairs.
I brushed Adele's hair and made her neat, and having ascertained that I was myself
in my usual quaker trim, where there was nothing to retouch, all being too close
and plain, braided locks included, to admit of disarrangement.
We descended.
Adele wondering whether the pity cough ray
was at length come, for owing to some mistake.
Its arrival had hitherto been delayed.
She was gratified.
There it stood, a little carton on the table when we entered the dining room.
She appeared to know it by instinct.
Ma boite, ma boite exclaimed she, running towards it.
Yes, there is your boite at last.
Take it into a corner, you genuine daughter of
Paris, and amuse yourself with disemboweling it.
Said the deep and rather sarcastic voice of Mr. Rochester, proceeding from the
depths of an immense easy chair at the fireside.
And mind, he continued, don't bother me with any details of the anatomical
process, or any notice of the condition of the entrails.
Let your operation be conducted in silence.
Tien's toire tranquille en font comprenne -tout.
Adele seemed scarcely to need the warning.
She had already retired to a sofa with her treasure,
and was busy untying the cord which secured the lid.
Having removed this impediment, and lifted certain silvery envelopes of
tissue paper, she merely exclaimed, oh, siel, kuke boe,
and then remained absorbed in ecstatic contemplation.
Is Miss Eyre there?
Now demanded the master, half rising from his seat to look round to the door,
near which I still stood.
Ah, well, come forward, be seated here.
He drew a chair near his own.
I am not fond of the prattle of children, he continued.
For all bachelor as I am, I have no pleasant associations connected with their lisp.
It would be intolerable to me to pass a whole evening, tet-a-tet with a brat.
Don't draw that chair farther off Miss Eyre.
Sit down exactly where I placed it.
If you please, that is, confound these civilities.
I continually forget them.
Nor do I particularly affect simple-minded old ladies.
By the by, I must have mine in mind.
It won't do to neglect her.
She is a fairfax or wet to one.
And blood is said to be thicker than water.
He rang, and dispatched an invitation to Mrs Fairfax, who soon arrived,
knitting basket in hand.
Good evening, madam.
I send to you for a charitable purpose.
I have forbidden Adele to talk to me about her
presence, and she is bursting with repulsion.
Have the goodness to serve her as auditress and interlocutress.
It will be one of the most benevolent acts you ever performed.
Adele, indeed, no sooner saw Mrs Fairfax, than she summoned her to her sofa,
and there quickly filled her lap with the porcelain,
the ivory, the wax and contents of her boite.
Pooring out meantime, explanations and raptures
in such broken English as she was mistress of.
Now I have performed the part of a good host, pursued Mr. Rochester, put my guests
into the way of amusing each other, I ought
to be at liberty to attend to my own pleasure.
Mr. Air, draw your chair still a little farther forward.
You are yet too far back.
I cannot see you without disturbing my position in this comfortable chair,
which I have no mind to do.
I did, as I was bid, though I would much rather have remained somewhat in the shade.
But Mr. Rochester had such a direct way of giving orders.
It seemed a matter of course to obey him promptly.
We were, as I have said, in the dining room.
The luster, which had been lit for dinner,
filled the room with a festal breadth of light.
The large fire was all red and clear.
The purple curtains hung rich and ample before the lofty window and lofty arch.
Everything was still, saved the subdued chat of a del.
She dared not speak loud.
And filling up each pause, the beating of winter rain against the pains.
Mr. Rochester, as he sat in his damace -covered chair,
looked different to what I had seen him look before.
Not quite so stern, much less gloomy.
There was a smile on his lips and his eyes sparkled, whether with wine or not,
I am not sure, but I think it very probable.
He was, in short, in his after-dinner mood, more expanded and genial and also
more self-indulgent than the frigid and rigid temper of the morning.
Still, he looked preciously grim, cushioning his massive head against the
swelling back of his chair and receiving the light of the
fire on his granite-hune features, and in his great dark eyes.
For he had great dark eyes and very fine eyes, too.
Not without a certain change in their depth, sometimes which, if it was not
softness, reminded you at least of that feeling.
He had been looking two minutes at the fire, and
I had been looking the same length of time at him.
When turning suddenly, he caught my gaze fastened on his physiognomy.
You examine me, Miss Eyre, said he.
Do you think me handsome?
I should, if I had deliberated, have replied to this question by something
conventionally vague and polite, but the answer
somehow slipped from my tongue before I was aware.
No, sir.
Ah, buy my word.
There is something singular about you, said he.
You have the air of a little non-net, quaint, quiet, grave and simple,
as you sit with your hands before you and your eyes generally bent on the carpet,
except by the by, when they are directed piercingly to my face, as just now,
for instance.
And when one asks you a question, or makes a remark to which you are obliged
to reply, you wrap out a round rejoinder, which, if not blunt, is at least brusque.
What do you mean by it, sir?
I was too plain, I beg your pardon.
I ought to have replied that it was not easy to give
an impromptu answer to a question about appearances.
That tastes mostly differ, and that beauty is
of little consequence or something of that sort.
You ought to have replied no such thing, beauty of little consequence indeed,
and so under pretense of softening the previous
outrage, of stroking and soothing me into placidity.
You stick a sly pen knife under my ear.
Go on.
What fault do you find with me, prey?
I suppose I have all my limbs and all my features like any other man.
Mr. Rochester, allow me to disown my first answer.
I intended no pointed repartee.
It was only a blunder.
Just so.
I think so, and you shall be answerable for it.
Criticize me.
Does my forehead not please you?
He lifted up the sable waves of hair which lay horizontally over his brow and showed
a solid enough mass of intellectual organs, but an abrupt deficiency where the
suave sign of benevolence should have risen.
Now, ma'am, am I a fool?
Far from it, sir, you would perhaps think me rude if
I inquired in return whether you are a philanthropist?
There again another stick of the pen knife when she pretended to pat my head.
And that is because I said I did not like the society of children and old women,
lobe it spoken.
No young lady, I am not a general philanthropist, but I bear a conscience.
And he pointed to the prominences which are said to indicate that faculty,
and which, fortunately for him, was sufficiently conspicuous, giving
indeed a marked breadth to the upper part of his head.
And besides, I once had a kind of rude tenderness of heart.
When I was as old as you, I was a feeling fellow enough, partial to the unfledged,
unfostored, and unlucky, but fortune has knocked me about since.
She has even needed me with her knuckles, and now I flatter myself I am hard and
tough as an India rubber ball, pervious though through a chink or two
still, and with one sentient point in the middle of the lump.
Yes, does that leave hope for me?
Hope of what, sir?
Of my final retransformation from India, rubber back to flesh?
Decidedly, he has had too much wine, I thought.
And I did not know what answer to make to his queer question.
How could I tell whether he was capable of being retransformed?
You looked very much puzzled, Miss Eyre, and though you are not pretty any more
than I am handsome, yet a puzzled air becomes you.
Besides, it is convenient, for it keeps those searching eyes of yours away from my
physiognomy, and bizzies them with the worsted flowers of the rug, so puzzle on.
Young lady, I am disposed to be gregarious and communicative tonight.
With this announcement, he rose from his chair and
stood, leaning his arm on the marble mantelpiece.
In that attitude, his shape was seen plainly as well as his face.
His unusual breadth of chest disproportionate almost to his length of limb.
I am sure most people would have thought him an ugly man, yet there was so much
unconscious pride in his port, so much ease in his demeanor, such a look
of complete indifference to his own external appearance, so haughty a reliance
on the power of other qualities intrinsic or adventitious to atone for the lack of
mere personal attractiveness, that in looking at him, one inevitably shared the
indifference, and even in a blind imperfect sense put faith in the confidence.
I am disposed to be gregarious and communicative tonight, he repeated,
and that is why I sent for you.
The fire and the chandelier were not sufficient company for
me, nor would Pylor have been, for none of these can talk.
A del is a degree better but still far below the mark.
Mrs. Fairfax Ditto, you, I am persuaded, can suit me if you will.
You puzzled me the first evening I invited you down here.
I have almost forgotten you since.
Other ideas have driven yours from my head, but tonight I am resolved to be at
ease, to dismiss what importunes and recall what pleases.
It would please me now to draw you out, to learn more of you, therefore speak.
Instead of speaking, I smiled, and not a very complacent or submissive smile, either.
Speak, he urged.
What about, sir?
Whatever you like, I leave both the choice of subject
and the manner of treating it entirely to yourself.
Accordingly, I sat and said nothing.
If he expects me to talk for the mere sake of talking and showing off, he will find
he has addressed himself to the wrong person, I thought.
You are dumb, miss air.
I was dumb still.
He bent his head a little towards me, and with a
single hasty glance seemed to dive into my eyes.
Stubborn, he said, and annoyed.
Ah, it is consistent.
I put my request in an absurd, almost insolent form.
Miss air, I beg your pardon.
The fact is, once for all, I don't wish to treat you like an inferior.
That is, correcting himself.
I claim only such superiority as must result from 20 years
difference in age and a century's advance in experience.
This is legitimate, at JTNs, as Adele would say.
And it is by virtue of this superiority and this alone.
That I desire you to have the goodness to talk to me a little now, and divert my
thoughts, which are galled with dwelling on one point, cankering as a rusty nail.
He had dainned an explanation, almost an apology, and I did not feel
insensible to his condescension and would not sign so.
I am willing to amuse you if I can, sir, quite willing.
But I cannot introduce a topic, because how do I know what will interest you?
Ask me questions, and I will do my best to answer them.
Then, in the first place, do you agree with me that I have a right to be a little
masterful, abrupt, perhaps exacting sometimes, on the grounds I stated,
namely, that I am old enough to be your father, and that I have battled through a
varied experience with many men of many nations, and roamed over half the globe
while you have lived quietly with one set of people in one house.
Do as you please, sir, that is no answer, or rather it is a very irritating,
because a very evasive one reply clearly.
I don't think, sir, you have a right to come on me, merely because you are older
than I, or because you have seen more of the world than I have.
Your claim to superiority depends on the use
you have made of your time and experience.
Hmpf, promptly spoken.
But I won't allow that, seeing that it would never suit my case as I have made an
indifferent, not to say a bad use of both advantages.
Leaving superiority out of the question then, you must still agree to receive my
orders now and then, without being peaked or hurt by the tone of command.
Will you?
I smiled.
I thought to myself Mr. Rochester is peculiar.
He seems to forget that he pays me £30 per annum for receiving his orders.
The smile is very well, said he, catching instantly the passing expression,
but speak too.
I was thinking, sir, that very few masters would trouble themselves to inquire
whether or not their paid subordinates were peaked and hurt by their orders.
Payed subordinates?
What?
You are my paid subordinate, are you?
Oh, yes, I'd forgotten the salary.
Well then, on that mercenary ground, will you agree to let me hector a little?
No, sir, not on that ground, but on the ground that you did forget it,
and that you care whether or not a dependent is
comfortable in his dependency, I agree heartily.
And will you consent to dispense with the great many conventional forms and phrases
without thinking that the omission arises from insolence?
I am sure, sir, I should never mistake informality for insolence, one I rather
like, the other nothing free-born would submit to even for a salary.
Humbug, most things free-born will submit to anything for a salary.
Therefore, keep to yourself and don't venture on
generalities of which you are intensely ignorant.
However, I mentally shake hands with you for your answer, despite its inaccuracy,
and as much for the manner in which it was said, as for the substance of the speech,
the manner was frank and sincere.
One does not often see such a manner.
No, on the contrary, affectation or coldness or stupid, course-minded
misapprehension of one's meaning are the usual rewards of candor.
Not three in three thousand raw school -girl governesses would have answered me
as you have just done, but I don't mean to flatter you.
If you are cast in a different mold to the majority, it is no merit of yours.
Nature did it, and then, after all, I go too fast in my conclusions.
For what I yet know, you may be no better than the rest.
You may have intolerable defects to counterbalance your few good points.
And so may you, I thought.
My eye met his, as the idea crossed my mind.
He seemed to read the glance, answering as if
its import had been spoken as well as imagined.
Yes, yes, you are right," said he.
I have plenty of faults of my own.
I know it, and I don't wish to palliate them, I assure you.
God would I need not be too severe about others.
I have a past existence, a series of deeds, a color of life to contemplate
within my own breast, which might well call my
snares and censures from my neighbours to myself.
I started, or rather, for like other defaulters, I like to lay half the blame
on ill fortune and adverse circumstances, was thrust onto a wrong tack at the age of
one and twenty, and have never recovered the right cause since.
But I might have been very different.
I might have been as good as you, wiser, almost astainless.
I envy you, your peace of mind, your clean conscience, your unpiluted memory.
Little girl, a memory without blot or contamination must be an exquisite
treasure, an inexhaustible source of pure refreshment, is it not?
How was your memory when you were eighteen, sir?
All right then, limpid, salubrius?
No gush of bilge water had turned it to fetid puddle.
I was your equal at eighteen, quite your equal.
Nature meant me to be, on the whole, a good man, miss
air, one of the better kind, and you see I am not so.
You would say you don't see it.
At least I flatter myself, I read as much in your eye, beware by the by what you
express with that organ I am quick at interpreting its language.
Then take my word for it.
I am not a villain, you are not to suppose that, not to attribute to me any such bad
eminence, but owing I verily believe, rather
to circumstances than to my natural bent.
I am a trite commonplace sinner, hackneyed in all the poor petty
dissipations, with which the rich and worthless tried to put on life.
Do you wonder that I avow this to you?
Know that in the course of your future life, you will often find yourself elected
the involuntary confidant of your acquaintances' secrets.
People will instinctively find out, as I have done, that it is not your forte
to tell of yourself, but to listen while others talk of themselves.
They will feel, too, that you listen with no malevolent scorn of their indiscretion,
but with a kind of innate sympathy.
Not the less comforting and encouraging, because
it is very unobtrusive in its manifestations.
How do you know?
How can you guess all this, sir?
I know it well.
Therefore, I proceed almost as freely as if I were writing my thoughts in a diary.
You would say, I should have been superior to circumstances, so I should,
so I should, but you see, I was not.
When fate wronged me, I had not the wisdom to remain cool.
I turned desperate.
Then I degenerated.
Now, when any vicious simpleton excites my disgust by his poultry, ribaldry,
I cannot flatter myself that I am better than he.
I am forced to confess that he and I are on a level.
I wish I had stood firm.
God knows I do.
Dred remorse when you attempted to err, Missiah.
Remorse is the poison of life.
Repentance is said to be its cure, sir.
It is not its cure.
Reformation may be its cure, and I could reform.
I have strength yet for that.
If, but where is the use of thinking of it?
Hampered, burdened, cursed as I am.
Besides, since happiness is irrevocably denied me, I have
a right to get pleasure out of life, and I will get it.
Cost what it may.
Then you will degenerate still more, sir.
Possibly, yet why should I, if I can get sweet fresh pleasure?
And I may get it as sweet and fresh as the wild honey the bee gathers on the more.
It will sting.
It will taste bitter, sir.
How do you know?
You never tried it.
How very serious.
How very solemn you look, and you are as ignorant of the matter as this cameo head,
taking one from the mantelpiece.
You have no right to preach to me, you neophyte, that have not passed the
porch of life, and are absolutely unequainted with its mysteries.
I only remind you of your own words, sir.
You said error brought remorse, and you pronounced remorse the poison of existence.
And who talks of error now?
I scarcely think the notion that flittered across my brain was an error.
I believe it was an inspiration, rather than a temptation.
It was very genial, very soothing.
I know that.
Here it comes again.
It is no devil I assure you, or if it be, it
has put on the robes of an angel of light.
I think I must admit so fair a guest, when it asks entrance to my heart.
Distrusted, sir, it is not a true angel.
Once more, how do you know?
By what instinct do you pretend to distinguish between a fallen serif of the
abyss and a messenger from the eternal throne, between a guide and a seducer?
I judged by your countenance, sir, which was troubled
when you said the suggestion had returned upon you.
I feel sure it will work you more misery if you listen to it.
Not at all.
It bears the most gracious message in the world.
For the rest, you are not my conscience keeper, so don't make yourself uneasy.
Here, come in, Bonnie Wanderer.
He said this as if he spoke to a vision, viewless to any eye but his own.
Then, folding his arms, which he had half extended on his chest, he seemed to
enclose in their embrace the invisible being.
Now, he continued again addressing me, I have received the pilgrim, a disguised
deity as I verily believe, already it has done me good.
My heart was a sort of channel, it will now be a shrine.
To speak truth, sir, I don't understand you at all.
I cannot keep up the conversation because it has got out of my depth.
Only one thing I know, you said you were not as good as you should like to be,
and that you regretted your own imperfection.
One thing I can comprehend.
You intimated that to have a sullied memory was a perpetual bane.
It seems to me that if you tried hard, you would in time find it possible to
become what you yourself would approve, and that if from this day you began with
resolution to correct your thoughts and actions.
You would in a few years have laid up a new and stainless store of recollections,
to which you might revert with pleasure.
Justly thought rightly said Messiah, and at
this moment I am paving hell with energy, sir.
I am laying down good intentions which I believe durable as flint.
Certainly, my associates and pursuits shall be other than they have been,
and better, and better.
So much better as pure awe is than foul draws.
You seem to doubt me.
I don't doubt myself.
I know what my aim is, what my motives are, and at this moment I pass a law,
unalterable as that of the Medis and Persians, that both are right.
They cannot be sir if they require a new statute to legalize them.
They are, miss air, though they absolutely require a new statute.
Unheard of combinations of circumstances demand unheard of rules.
That sounds a dangerous maxim, sir, because
one can see at once that it is liable to abuse.
Sententious sage, so it is.
But I swear by my household gods not to abuse it.
You are human and fallible.
I am.
So are you.
What then?
The human and fallible should not irrigate a power with
which the divine and perfect alone can be safely entrusted.
What power?
That of saying, of any strange unsanctioned line of action, let it be right.
Let it be right.
The very words you have pronounced them.
May it be right then, I said, as I rose, deeming it useless
to continue a discourse which was all darkness to me.
And besides, sensible that the character of my interlocutor was beyond my
penetration, at least beyond its present reach.
And feeling the uncertainty, the vague sense of
insecurity which accompanies a conviction of ignorance.
Where are you going?
To put a del to bed, it is past her bedtime.
You are afraid of me because I talk like a sphinx.
Your language is enigmatical, sir.
But though I am bewildered, I am certainly not afraid.
You are afraid.
Your self-love dreads a blunder.
In that sense, I do feel apprehensive.
I have no wish to talk nonsense.
If you did, it would be in such a grave, quiet manner, I should mistake it for sense.
Do you never laugh, miss air?
Don't trouble yourself to answer.
I see you laugh rarely, but you can laugh very merrily.
Believe me, you are not naturally austere, any more than I am naturally vicious.
The low wood constraint still clings to you somewhat, controlling your features,
muffling your voice, and restricting your limbs.
And you fear in the presence of a man and a brother, or father, or master,
or what you will, to smile too galley, speak too freely, or move too quickly.
But in time, I think you will learn to be natural with
me, as I find it impossible to be conventional with you.
And then your looks and movements will have more
vivacity and variety than they dare offer now.
I see it intervals, the glance of a curious sort
of bird through the close set bars of a cage.
A vivid, restless, resolute captive is there.
Were it but free?
It would soar cloud high.
You are still bent on going.
It has struck nine, sir.
Never mind.
Wait a minute.
A del is not ready to go to bed yet.
My position, miss air, with my back to the fire
and my face to the room, favours observation.
While talking to you, I have also occasionally watched a del.
I have my own reasons for thinking her a curious study, reasons that I may,
nay that I shall impart to you some day.
She pulled out of her box about ten minutes ago, a little pink silk frock,
wrapped a lit her face as she unfolded it.
Coquetry runs in her blood, blends with her
brains, and seasons the marrow of her bones.
Ylfoca Julesse cried, she, et a lint storm mim.
And she rushed out of the room.
She is now with Sufi, undergoing a robing process.
In a few minutes, she will reenter.
And I know what I shall see, a miniature of Celine Varan, as she used to appear on
the boards at the rising of... but never mind that.
However, my tenderest feelings are a bout to receive a shock.
Such is my presentiment.
Stay now, to see whether it will be realized.
Erlong, Adele's little foot was heard tripping across the hall.
She entered, transformed as her guardian had predicted.
A dress of rose-colored satin, very short.
And as full in the skirt as it could be gathered,
replaced the brown frock she had previously worn.
A wreath of rose-budds circled her forehead.
Her feet were dressed in silk stockings and small white satin sandals.
Esset que marob va bien, cried she, bounding forwards, aimé sou liés,
aimé bas, tenez, je crois que je vais danser.
And spreading out her dress, she chasse across the room till, having reached Mr.
Rocheste.
She wheeled lightly round before him, on tiptoe,
then dropped on one knee at his feet, exclaiming.
Then rising she added, ses comcelles que m 'amont faisait, n'est-ce pas monsieur,
précise-les was the answer, and comcelle.
She charmed my English gold out of my British British pocket.
I have been green too, Miss Eyre.
I, grass green, not a more vernal tint, freshens you now than once freshened me.
My spring is gone, however, but it has left me that French flowerette on my
hands, which, in some moods, I would feign be rid of.
Not valuing now the root once its sprang, having found that it was of a sort which
nothing but gold dust could manure, I have but half a liking to the blossom,
especially when it looks so artificial as just now.
I keep it and rear it rather on the Roman Catholic principle
of expiating numerous sins, great or small, by one good work.